In this first video, I'd
like to share with you
an overview of how LLMs, Large
Language Models, work.
We'll go into how they are trained, as
well as details like the
tokenizer and how that can
affect the output of when
you prompt an LLM.
And we'll also take a look at
the chat format for LLMs, which
is a way of
specifying both system as
well as user messages
and understand what you
can do with that capability. Let's
take a look. First, how does
a Large Language Model work?
You're probably familiar with
the text generation
process where you
can give a prompt, "I
love eating", and ask an LLM to
fill in what the
things are likely completions
given this prompt. And
it may say, "Bagels
with cream cheese, or
my mother's meatloaf, or out
with friends".
But how did the model learn to do this?
The main tool used to train an LLM
is actually supervised learning.
In supervised learning,
a computer learns an input-output
or X or Y mapping
using labeled training data. So
for example, if you're using
supervised learning to
learn to classify the sentiment of
restaurant reviews, you might
collect a training set
like this, where a
review like, "The pastrami
sandwich is great!", is labeled
as a positive sentiment review, and
so on.
And "Service was slow,
the food was so-so.", it
was negative, and "The
earl grey tea was fantastic.", has
a positive label.
By the way,
both Isa and I were born in the UK,
and so both of us
like our earl grey tea.
And so the process
for supervised learning is
typically to get labeled
data and then train
AI model on data.
And after training,
you can then deploy
and call the model and give it a
new restaurant review like
best pizza I've ever had.
You hopefully output that
as a positive sentiment.
It turns out that
supervised learning is a
core building block for
training Large Language Models.
Specifically, a Large Language
Model can be built by using
supervised learning to
repeatedly predict the next word.
Let's say that in your training sets
of a lot of text data, you
have to sentence, "My
favorite food is a bagel
with cream cheese and lox.".
Then this sentence is turned into
a sequence of training examples,
where given a sentence fragment,
"My favorite food is a",
if you want to predict the
next word in this case was "bagel",
or given the sentence
fragment or sentence prefix,
"My favorite food is a bagel",
the next word in this case would be
"with", and so on.
And given a large training set
of hundreds of
billions or sometimes
even more words, you can then create
a massive training set
where you can start
off with part of a sentence or part
of a piece of
text and repeatedly ask
the language model to
learn to predict what
is the next word.
So today there are
broadly two major types
of Large Language Models.
The first is a "Base LLM"
and the second,
which is what is increasingly used,
is the "Instruction Tuned LLM".
So the base LLM
repeatedly predicts the next
word based on text training data.
And so if I give it a prompt,
"Once upon a time there was a unicorn",
then it may,
by repeatedly predicting one
word at a time, come up with a
completion that tells a
story about a unicorn
living in a magical
forest with all her unicorn friends.
Now, a downside of this is that
if you were to prompt it with
"What is the capital of France?",
quite possible that on
the internet there might
be a list of
quiz questions about France.
So it may complete this with
"What is France's largest city, what
is France's population?", and so
on.
But what you really
want is you want it to tell you
what is the capital of France,
probably,
rather than list all these questions.
So an Instruction Tuned LLM instead
tries to follow
instructions and will hopefully say,
"The capital of France is Paris.".
How do you go from a
Base LLM to an Instruction Tuned
LLM? This is what the process of
training an Instruction Tuned LLM,
like ChatGPT, looks like.
You first train a Base
LLM on a lot of data,
so hundreds of billions of words,
maybe even more. And this is a
process that can take
months on a large
supercomputing system.
After you've trained the Base LLM, you
would then further train
the model by fine-tuning it
on a smaller set of examples, where the
output follows an input instruction. And
so, for example, you may
have contractors help you
write a lot of examples of an instruction,
and then a good response to
an instruction.
And that creates a
training set to carry
out this additional fine-tuning. So
that learns to predict what is
the next word if it's trying
to follow an instruction. After that,
to improve
the quality of the LLM's output, a
common process now is to obtain human ratings
of the quality of many different
LLM outputs on criteria, such as
whether
the output is helpful, honest, and harmless.
And you can then
further tune the LLM
to increase the probability
of its generating the
more highly rated outputs.
And the most common technique
to do this is RLHF, which stands
for Reinforcement Learning from
Human Feedback.
And whereas training the
Base LLM can take months,
the process of going
from the Base LLM
to the Instruction Tuned
LLM can be done in maybe days on
a much more modest size data sets,
and much more
modest size computational resources.
So this is how you would use an LLM.
I'm gonna import a few libraries.
I'm
going to load my OpenAI key here. I'll
say a little bit more about this
later in this video.
And here's a helper function to get
a completion given a prompt.
If you have not
yet installed the OpenAI
package on your computer,
you might have to
run pip install OpenAI.
But I already have it installed here,
so I won't run that.
And let me hit Shift-Enter
to run these. And
now I can set "response = get_completion".
What
is the capital of France?
And hopefully it will
give me a good result.
Now, in the description of the
Large Language Model so far,
I talked about it as
predicting one word at a time,
but there's actually one more
important technical detail.
If you were to tell it,
take the letters in the word lollipop,
and reverse them,
this seems like an easy task,
maybe like a four-year-old could
do this task.
But if you were to
ask ChatGPT to do this,
it actually outputs a
somewhat garbled whatever this is.
This is not L-O-L-I-P-O-P, this is not lollipop's letters reversed.
So why is ChatGPT
unable to do
what seems like a relatively simple task? It
turns out that there's one more
important detail for how a
Large Language Model works,
which is it doesn't
actually repeatedly predict the
next word, it instead
repeatedly predicts the
next token.
And what an LLM actually does is it
will take a sequence of characters,
like "Learning new things is fun!",
and group the
characters together to
form tokens that
comprise commonly occurring
sequences of characters.
So here, learning new things is fun,
each of them is a fairly common word,
and so each token
corresponds to one word,
or one word in a space,
or an exclamation mark.
But if you were to
give it input with some
somewhat less frequently used words,
like
"Prompting as powerful developer tool.",
the word prompting is
still not that common
in the English language,
but certainly gaining in popularity.
And so prompting is actually broken
down to three tokens with "'prom", "pt",
and "ing", because those three
are commonly occurring
sequences of letters.
And if you were to
give it the word lollipop,
the tokenizer actually breaks
this down into three tokens, "l"
and "oll" and "ipop".
And because ChatGPT isn't
seeing the individual letters, is
instead seeing these three tokens, it's
more difficult for it to
correctly print out these
letters in reverse order.
So here's
a trick you can use to fix this.
If I were to add
dashes to the word dashes,
between these letters,
and spaces would work too,
or other things would work too,
and tell it to take the letters and
lollipop and reverse them,
then it actually does
a much better job, this L-O-L-L-I-P-O-P.
And the reason for that is,
if you pass it lollipop
with dashes in between the letters,
it tokenizes each
of these characters
into an individual token,
making it easier for it to see the
individual letters and print
them out in reverse order.
So if you ever want to
use ChatGPT to play a word game,
like word or scrabble or something,
this nifty trick helps
it to better see
the individual letters of the words.
For the English language,
one token roughly on average,
corresponds to about four
characters or about three
quarters of a word.
And so different
Large Language Models
will often have different limits on
the number of input plus output
tokens it can accept.
The input is often called the context,
and the output is
often called the completion.
And the model GPT 3.5 Turbo, for
example, the
most commonly used chat GPT model, has
a limit of roughly 4,000 tokens
in the input plus output.
So if you try to
feed it an input context that's
much longer than this, it'll actually
throw an exception or
generate an error. Next, I
want to share with you
another powerful way to
use an LLM API.
Which involves specifying separate
system, user, and assistant messages.
Let me show you an example,
then we can explain
in more detail what it's
actually doing.
Here's a new helper function called "get_completion_from_messages",
and when we prompt
this LLM, we are going to
give it multiple messages.
Here's an example of what
you can do. I'm going to specify first a
message in the role of a
system, so this is a system message,
and the content of the system
message is "You are
an assistant who responds
in the style of Dr.
Seuss."
Then I'm
going to specify a user message, so
the role of the second message is "role
: user",
and the content of this is
"write me a very short
poem about a happy carrot".
And so let's run that, and with "temperature
= 1",
I actually never know what's
going to come out, but okay, that's a
cool poem. "Oh, how jolly
is this carrot that I see?".
And it actually rhymes pretty well.
All right, well done ChatGPT.
And so in this example,
the system message specifies
the overall tone of
what you want the
Large Language Model to do,
and the user message is a
specific instruction that
you wanted to carry out given
this higher level behavior that was
specified in the system message.
Here's
an illustration of how it all works.
So this is how the chat format works.
The system message sets
the overall tone of
behavior of the Large
Language Model or the assistant,
and then when you
give the user message,
such as maybe, such as
"Tell me a joke" or "Write me a poem",
it will then output an appropriate
response following what
you asked for in the user
message and consistent
with the overall behavior set in
the system message.
And by the way, although I'm
not illustrating it here, if
you want to use this in a multi-term conversation,
you can also input assistant
messages in this
messages format to let ChatGPT know
what it had previously said if
you wanted to continue the conversation
based on things
that it had previously said as
well.
But here are a few more examples.
If you want to set the tone,
to tell it to have
a one sentence long output,
then in the system message,
I can say all your
responses must be one sentence long.
And when I execute this,
it outputs a single sentence. It's
no longer a poem, not
in the style of Dr. Seuss, but
it's a single sentence. There's a story
about the happy carrot. And if we
want to combine both, specify the style
and the length, then I can
use the system message
to say, "You are an
assistant who responds in the
style of Dr. Seuss. All your sentences
must be one sentence
long.".
And now, this generates a
nice one sentence poem.
It was always smiling and never scary.
I like that. That's
a very happy poem.
And then lastly, just for fun,
if you are using an
LLM and you want to
know how many tokens are you using,
here's a helper function that
is a little bit
more sophisticated in that
it gets a response
from the OpenAI API
endpoint and then it
uses other values in
the response to tell
you how many prompt tokens, completion
tokens, and
total tokens were used
in your API call. Let
me define that.
And if I run this now, here's
the response.
And here is accounts of
how many tokens we use.
So this output,
which had 55 tokens,
whereas the prompt input had 37 tokens.
So this used up 92 tokens altogether.
When I'm
using LL Models in practice, I
don't worry that much, frankly, about the
number of tokens I'm using.
Maybe one case where it
might be worth checking the
number of tokens is if you're
worried that the user
might have given you
too long an input
that exceeds the 4,000 or
so token limits of ChatGPT, in which
case you could double
check how many tokens
it was and truncate
it to make sure you're staying within
the input token limits
of the large language
model.
Now, I want to share with
you one more tip for
how to use a Large Language Model.
Commonly the OpenAI API requires
using an API key that's
tied to either a free
or a paid account.
And so many developers
will write the API
key in plain text
like this into their
Jupyter notebook.
And this is a less secure way of
using API keys that
I would not recommend you use,
because it's just too easy to
share this notebook with
someone else or check
this into GitHub or
something and thus end
up leaking your API
key to someone else.
In contrast, what you saw me
do in the Jupyter
notebook was this piece of code,
where I use a library "dotenv",
and then run this command "load_dotenv",
"find_dotenv" to read
a local file which is called ".env" that
contains my secret key.
And so with this code snippet,
I have locally stored a file called
".env" that contains my API key.
And this loads it into the
operating systems environmental
variable.
And then "os.getenv, ('OPENAI_API_KEY')" stores it
into this variable. And in this
whole process, I don't ever have to
enter the API key in plain text and
unencrypted plain text into
my Jupyter notebook.
So this is a relatively
more secure and a better
way to access the API key.
And in fact, this is a general
method for storing different
API keys from lots
of different online services
that you might want to use and call
from your Jupyter notebook.
Lastly, I think the degree to which
prompting is revolutionizing
AI application development
is still underappreciated.
In the traditional
supervised machine learning
workflow, like the restaurant
review sentiment classification
example that I touched on just now,
if you want to build a
classifier to classify
restaurant review positive
and negative sentiments,
you at first get a bunch of label data,
maybe hundreds of examples.
This might take, I don't know, weeks,
maybe a month.
Then you would train a model
on data and getting an appropriate
open source model,
tuning on the model, evaluating it.
That might take days, weeks,
maybe even a few months.
And then you might have to find a
cloud service to deploy it,
and then get your
model uploaded to the cloud,
and then run the model,
and finally be able to call your model.
And it's again not uncommon for this
to take a team a
few months to get working.
In contrast with prompting-based
machine learning, when
you have a text application, you
can specify a prompt.
This can take minutes, maybe hours,
if you need to iterate a few times
to get an effective prompt.
And then in hours,
maybe at most days,
but frankly more often hours,
you can have this running
using API calls and start
making calls to the model.
And once you've done that, in
just again, maybe
minutes or hours, you
can start calling the model and
start making inferences. And
so there are applications
that used to take
me maybe six months or a year to
build, that you can now build
in minutes or hours, maybe
very small numbers of
days using prompting. And this is revolutionizing
what AI applications
can be built quickly.
One important caveat,
this applies to
many unstructured data applications,
including specifically
text applications and maybe
increasingly vision applications,
although the vision
technology is much
less mature right now, but it's
kind of getting there.
This recipe doesn't really work for
structured data applications, meaning
machine learning applications
on tabular data
with lots of numerical values in
Excel spreadsheets.
But for applications to
which this does apply,
the fact that AI components
can be built so quickly,
is changing the workflow
of how the entire
system might be built.
Building an entire system
might still take days
or weeks or something,
but at least this piece of
it can be done much faster.
And so with that, let's
go on to the next video, where
Isa will show how to use
these components to
evaluate the input to a customer
service assistant.
And this will be part of a bigger
example that you see
developed through this course,
for building a
customer service assistant
for an online retailer.